Guide to the Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records 1948-1983, undated (bulk 1959-1979) MS 3009-RG 6.I MS 3009-RG 6TEST
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Corporate Editorial Records TEST
1944-1998, undated (bulk 1959-1987)
MS 3009-RG 6TEST
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
130.0 Linear feet (130 boxes)
The Corporate Editorial Records contain records from editorial staff working at the corporate level overseeing all publications at Time Inc. This includes the editor-in-chief, editorial director, corporate editor, and assistant corporate editor. Staff represented include Editors-in-Chief Hedley Donovan, Henry Anatole Grunwald, and Jason McManus.
Time, inc.
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Accruals Note
Further additions to this finding aid are expected.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Related records outside of the New-York Historical Society include:
Hedley Donovan papers, University Archives, University of Minnesota, Twin Cities.
Henry A. Grunwald papers, Library of Congress Manuscript Division Washington, D.C., https://lccn.loc.gov/mm2005085225.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include privileged attorney correspondence; student records; medical records; personnel performance evaluations; contracts and agreements; and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in boxes R10, R12, and R18-R19. Materials created within the past 35 years also may be subject to restriction on a case-by-case basis. Unreformatted audiovisual material in the collection is not accessible.
Historical Note
The office of Editor-in-Chief did not exist at the formation of Time Inc. since the company initially had only Time as its major publication. Cofounders Henry R. Luce and Briton Hadden were both listed on the Time masthead as editors from 1923 through Hadden's death in 1929. Though both were listed, their agreement in practice was to swap positions as the heads of editorial and business.
After Hadden's death, John S. Martin became the managing editor of Time with Luce listed above him as editor. According to Robert T. Elson, writer of the authorized history of Time Inc., Luce was using the title of editor-in-chief in 1938 when he resigned as Time Inc.'s president and chief operating officer, but retained his roles as board chairman and editor-in-chief.
According to Time Inc.'s history on the company intranet, Luce restructured the management of the magazines in 1937, giving each a publisher, a managing editor, and an advertising director. This restructuring established the separation of the business side from the editorial side, respectively referred to as church and state by staff. Luce formalized these roles and the importance of separating them in a 1938 memo entitled "The Principles, Policies, Attitudes Etc. Which Govern and Motivate Time Inc." It is possible this restructuring is when Luce took on the title Editor-in-Chief although he isn't listed as such on magazine mastheads or in the annual reports until the 1940s. According to the intranet, Luce wrote a note to Hedley Donovan, his pick for next editor-in-chief, in 1962 reiterating the necessity of the independence of the office.
Editor-in-Chief was the top editorial position at Time Inc., overseeing editorial policies and standards for all titles and divisions including magazines, books and newspapers. The entire editorial side reported up to this position, and the editor-in-chief reported directly to the board. The publishing/business side reported up to top business executive which became the chief executive officer around 1960. In 1978, shortly before his retirement, Donovan presented a statement to the board to precisely define the role of editor-in-chief so that the office would be preserved for future holders. This statement was formally adopted as company policy in December 1978. In April 1986, succeeding Editor-in-Chief Henry Grunwald further updated the definition of the title in a statement to the board, a copy of which is in Ray Cave's files.
After the merger of Time Inc. and Warner Communications in 1990 when the magazine and books divisions became subsidiaries, the editor-in-chief began reporting to the head of Time Warner blurring the editorial and publishing/business separation. In 2014 when Time Inc. disaffiliated from Time Warner, the editor-in-chief was replaced by the chief content officer reporting to the chief executive officer which removed the separation altogether.
Citations:
Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 8 May 2017.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
Scope and Contents Note
The Corporate Editorial Records contain records from editorial staff working at the corporate level. This includes the editor-in-chief, editorial director, corporate editor, and assistant corporate editor. These positions oversaw editorial work on all publications at Time Inc.
Series I. Editor-in-Chief Files contain the professional files of Time Inc. editors-in-chief beginning with Hedley Donovan, the second person to hold this title, followed by his successor Henry Anatole Grunwald, then Jason McManus.
Arrangement Note
Organized into three series:
Series I. Editor-in-Chief
Series II. Editorial Director
Series III. Corporate Editor
Donovan, Hedley; Grunwald, Henry A., (Henry Anatole); Appointment books; Corporation records; Corporations--History; Corporations--New York (State)--New York; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York; Organization files; Publishers and publishing--New York (State)--New York; Speeches (documents); Time, inc -- History; Time, inc -- Management
- Series I. Editor-in-Chief: Subseries I.A. Hedley Donovan Files, 1948-1983, undated (bulk 1959-1979); 56.0 Linear feet; (56 boxes)
  Biographical Note
  Hedley Donovan was the second editor-in-chief of Time Inc. from 1964 to 1979, a position previously held only by the company's cofounder Henry R. Luce.
  Donovan was a native of Minnesota and after graduating from the University of Minnesota, he spent three years at Oxford University studying history on a Rhodes scholarship. Instead of accepting a Harvard teaching assistant position, after graduation Donovan took the better paying job as a reporter at the Washington Post working on general and political assignments. During World War II, he served in Naval Intelligence.
  Fortune hired Donovan as a writer in 1945, promoting him to associate managing editor around 1950 and managing editor by 1953. In July 1959, Time Inc. announced Donovan's new position as editorial director, a deputy position to the editor-in-chief. While editorial director, Donovan established the Research and Development unit to conduct studies regarding Time Inc.'s ventures in television programming. In 1962, he was named to the board of directors. When Luce retired in April 1964, he recommended that the board appoint Donovan as his replacement.
  During his tenure as editor-in-chief, Donovan made the decision to suspend publishing of Life in 1972 for financial reasons and launched the magazines Money (1972) and People (1974). Under his supervision, the Magazine Development Group also considered other new magazine ideas: Well, regarding health topics; Camera Month; View, the description of which sounds like a precursor to People; and a women's magazine. Though the women's magazine received a title ( Woman), and several years of work went into it, it was never realized. Time Inc. also acquired the Washington Star newspaper near the end of Donovan's tenure.
  In 1978, shortly before his retirement, Donovan presented a statement to the board to precisely define the role of editor-in-chief so that the office would be preserved for future holders. As transcribed in Prendergast and Colvin's book The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980, he stated: "[The editor-in-chief] is responsible solely to the board for editorial content." "The board... delegates to the editor-in-chief the continuing appraisal and direction of the company's editorial work." "The editor-in-chief is a member of the board and of its executive committee." "The board does not expect the editor-in-chief to maintain the same immediate authority over the editorial work of Books and the [Washington] Star as he does over the magazines. He will, however, appoint the managing editor of Books and the editor of the Star..."
  His statement also defined the relationship of the editorial director as senior deputy to the editor-in-chief. This statement was formally adopted as company policy in December 1978.
  While preparing for retirement, Donovan recommended his replacement be Henry Grunwald with Ralph Graves as the editorial director. Donovan retired as editor-in-chief in June 1979. F.Y.I., the Time Inc. staff newsletter published a special issue of articles about Donovan on June 4, 1979. Though officially retired from Time Inc., Donovan remained a consultant until at least 1985.
  After Donovan's retirement, he wanted to take some of his files in order to write his memoirs. Two sets of copies were made, one for the Archives and one for the researchers and writers working on the history of Time Inc. book. The original materials may be in the papers Donovan's family donated to the University Archives at the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities.
  Beginning in July 1979, Donovan served approximately one year as a White House senior advisor to President Jimmy Carter. In 1981, he was the visiting journalist at Harvard University, and in 1989 Donovan published his memoirs Right Places, Right Times: Forty Years in Journalism, Not Counting My Paper Route.
  Citations:
  Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
  Elson, Robert T., and Duncan Norton-Taylor. 1973. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1941-1960. New York: Atheneum.
  Bill Hooper, email to Holly Deakyne, 22 February 2017.
  Jimmy Carter: "Senior Adviser to the President Appointment of Hedley W. Donovan.," July 25, 1979. Online by Gerhard Peters and John T. Woolley, The American Presidency Project. http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/?pid=32649.
  Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into seven subsubseries:
  Subsubseries I.A.1. Appointment Books
  Subsubseries I.A.2. Expense Reports
  Subsubseries I.A.3. Research and Development Reports
  Subsubseries I.A.4. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations
  Subsubseries I.A.5. Subject Files
  Subsubseries I.A.6. Trips
  Subsubseries I.A.7. Audiovisual
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Hedley Donovan Files contain the files kept by his office while he was editorial director and editor-in-chief. The files also include some records or copies of records up to four years after his retirement. The files document his schedule, professional expenses, collected research reports, speeches, office subject files, and travel.
  - Subsubseries I.A.1. Subject Files, 1948-1983; 35.0 Linear feet; (35 boxes)
    Organized into four groups: two groups of folders designated by date ranges, one run of original alphabetical folders, and one run of duplicate alphabetical folders. The groups of folders designated by date range are in the same order as they were in the Time Inc. archives, and the group names are from labels on the shelf or drawer where they were housed. The arrangement for the alphabetical files is based on the original order which alphabetized by topic.
    The Subject Files contain the majority of Donovan's correspondence and other office files and work product including remarks at board meetings; event invitations; press clippings; internal correspondence and memoranda; and correspondence from former and future United States presidents along with Congress members, heads of companies, presidents and directors at universities, and other notable people. The Subject Files folders are frequently labeled on the front cover in handwriting which looks like Donovan's. Some of the files contain cross-reference sheets indicating the Time Inc. Archives completed some work.
    The files labeled as "1959-1979" and "1969-1978" are two groups of files that are labeled similarly to the alphabetical Subject Files and found together as folders and loose material. This might be material removed for research purposes, by Donovan or someone else, and not refiled into the original folders. Materials within each group have a loose topical relationship, and similar topics are in the alphabetically organized Subject Files. For "1959-1979" the majority of the materials were loose. The topics cover politics, United States presidents from Kennedy to Carter, and other politicians during this era. For "1969-1978" the majority of the materials were loose, and cover three topical areas: suspension of Life, research on the press, and speeches or talks.
    The miscellaneous files within the alphabetical run contain primarily correspondence along with article proposals, request for issues of magazines, complaints about facts in articles, thank yous, and memos regarding staff, correspondence with board members such as Sol M. Linowitz and Thomas J. Watson, Jr., and extensive correspondence from several notable people including Malcom Forbes, Gaylord Freeman, Jr., George McGhee, Arthur "Red" Motley, Elmo Roper, Dean Rusk, and John Volpe. Some items of note in the miscellaneous files include a letter from the U.S. Embassy regarding Mrs. Gandhi (in "B-Miscellaneous"); letters from Buckminster Fuller describing "Spaceship Earth"; and a letter from Florida senator Billy Graham regarding Time's Black Panther articles. Even when there is a specific file on a person or event, additional records may be in the respective miscellaneous file, such as with Herman Nickel, John Oakes, Carl Solberg, and Cyrus Vance.
    In order to get background information on people or places and to stay apprised of current events and trends, Donovan utilized research assistants to write briefs on various topics. Briefs from Time reporter Dorothy "Dottie" Ferenbaugh are the most prevalent in Donovan's files. There are extensive research memos from Ferenbaugh in her own file as well as throughout the Subject Files on topics including: number of deaths of Black Panther party members due to encounters with the police; women's magazines; Time Inc. stockholders; summaries of New York Times articles; Time's association with university curriculum; Time's coverage of Guatemala; and the publishing industry.
    Other items of interest include the compiled critiques on Time from throughout the United States and Canada found in "Attitudes", and the specifics on Donovan's business meetings in the "Lunches and Dinners" files which contain attendee and special guest lists, invitations, agenda, and correspondence.
    The duplicate Subject Files may contain material not represented in the original alphabetical files although they include similar topics.
    - Duplicates: Edit: Leadership cover, method, Time reportage? Futures, 1974 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 17)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Luncheon guests and correspondence, 1973 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 18)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Middle East: 1969 May (Offsite-box 756, Folder 19)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Seamon's report on back of book, Time: 1974 December (Offsite-box 756, Folder 20)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Shield laws, first amendment, press councils, Hedley Donovan Speech at Creativity Conference: Southbury, CT: 1972 November 2 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 21)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Staff Mixers, 1971-1975 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 22)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Time Inc. consultants fees: 1974 October (Offsite-box 756, Folder 23)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Time Inc. and shield laws: 1973 February 8 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 24)
    - Duplicates: Edit: Vietnam: Research, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 25)
    - Duplicates: Edit: World-U.S. GNP, 1972 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 26)
    - Duplicates: Edit: America: Jimmy Carter research and tear sheets: 1973 December 3 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 27)
    - Duplicates: Edit: America: Mrs. Luce's view of Time Editorial requesting Nixon resignation, 1973 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 28)
    - Duplicates: Edit: America: New Congress, 1973 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 29)
    - Duplicates: Edit: America: Time press files on background for Time story on subpoenas: 1973 March (Offsite-box 756, Folder 30)
    - Duplicates: Edit: America: Watergate memos to Hedley Donovan: 1973 June (Offsite-box 756, Folder 31)
    - Duplicates: Edit: China: Teng interview, 1979 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 32)
    - Duplicates: Ferenbaugh's WPFC research, 1978 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 33)
    - Duplicates: Fortune, 1972-1976 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 34)
    - Duplicates: Fortune: Sales Convention: Ponte Vedra: 1968 May 21 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 35)
    - Duplicates: Fortune: 50th anniversary talk: 1980 February 4 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 36)
    - Duplicates: Harvard: John F. Kennedy School Seminars: 1981 April-May (Offsite-box 756, Folder 37-38)
    - Duplicates: Harvard: Misc., 1979-1983 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 39)
    - Duplicates: Hunt/Donovan/Graves Ball: 1969 June 12 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 40)
    - Duplicates: Leadership issue, 1976 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 41)
    - Duplicates: Legal: Burger and press subpoenas: 1973 March (Offsite-box 756, Folder 42)
    - Duplicates: Legal: Shield law papers: 1973 March (Offsite-box 756, Folder 43)
    - Duplicates: Life, 1969-1972 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 44-46)
    - Duplicates: Life: Misc., 1979 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 47)
    - Duplicates: Life: Astronauts [RESTRICTED], 1963 (Offsite-box R10, Folder 18)
    - Duplicates: Life: Best of Life research books, 1974 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 48)
    - Duplicates: Life: Circulation material: Sutton-Loomis, pending: 1972 April 26 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 49)
    - Duplicates: Life: Covers, 1961 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 50)
    - Duplicates: Life: Critiques of, 1960-1963 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 51)
    - Duplicates: Life: Edit: Cocktail party: 1974 January 3 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 52)
    - Duplicates: Life: Edit: Staff meeting: 1971 December 1: Ralph Graves (Offsite-box 756, Folder 53)
    - Duplicates: Life: Foreign policy round table: 1963 May 3 (Offsite-box 756, Folder 54)
    - Duplicates: Life: General, 1959-1968 (Offsite-box 756-757)
    - Duplicates: Life: General foods test, 1970 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 2)
    - Duplicates: Life: George Washington papers, 1968 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 3)
    - Duplicates: Life: Issues comments, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 4)
    - Duplicates: Life: Memos to the editors, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 5)
    - Duplicates: Life: Mid-1963 discussions (Offsite-box 757, Folder 6)
    - Duplicates: Life: "New Life" memos, 1961 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 7)
    - Duplicates: Life: New York Edition, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 8)
    - Duplicates: Life: Petition against Nixon endorsement by Life, 1972 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 9)
    - Duplicates: Life: Photographic contest, 1970 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 10)
    - Duplicates: Life: Readership analysis: 1971 November 30 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 11)
    - Duplicates: Life: Space tour: 1969 July 14-17 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 12)
    - Duplicates: Life: Supplements, 1962 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 13)
    - Duplicates: Life: Tax round table: 1962 December 17 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 14)
    - Duplicates: Life: Top management shifts, 1961 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 15)
    - Duplicates: Life: Various letters, 1970 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 16)
    - Duplicates: Life: Vietnam: 1967 June 2 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 17)
    - Duplicates: Life: "What is Life" memos, 1966 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 18)
    - Duplicates: Life: Year-end issues, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 19)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R., 1963-1967 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 20)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: McKinsey Lectures: Columbia University, 1963 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 21)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Memos, 1948-1963 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 22-27)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Proposed Russia visit, 1961 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 28)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Reappraisal, 1954 (Offsite-box 727, Folder 29)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Round the world trip, 1960 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 30)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Speeches, 1956-1963 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 31)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R.: Telegrams, messages, etc., 1967 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 32)
    - Duplicates: Luce, Henry R. Foundation, 1968 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 33)
    - Duplicates: Luce Memorial, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 34-35)
    - Duplicates: Luce Memorial: Dedication: Washington, D.C.: 1972 May 23 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 36)
    - Duplicates: Lunch: 1966 December 20 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 37)
    - Duplicates: Lunches and Dinners: Edit and Kissinger, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 38)
    - Duplicates: Money, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 39)
    - Duplicates: Money: Editorial staff meetings: 1977 March 27 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 40)
    - Duplicates: Money: Research: 1973 October-November (Offsite-box 757, Folder 41)
    - Duplicates: Names: A-Z: Misc., 1970-1982 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 42)
    - Duplicates: Names: Personal: A-Z: Misc., 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 43)
    - Duplicates: Names Personal: Cranston, Alan, 1981 (Offsite-box 757, Folder 44)
    - Duplicates: People, 1975 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 1)
    - Duplicates: Personal: Time Inc., 1945-1952 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 2)
    - Duplicates: Pieces by Hedley Donovan: Annual Report, Time, Life, Fortune, etc, 1966-1970, 1979 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 3)
    - Duplicates: Piece for annual report, 1960-1969 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 4-5)
    - Duplicates: Postal matters, 1971 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 6)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Cambridge seminar plans: 1974 January 7-8: General correspondence (Offsite-box 758, Folder 7)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Cambridge seminar: 1974 January 7-8: Miscellaneous, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 8)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Cambridge conference: Letters of thanks: 1974 January 7-8 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 9)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: National Council Papers: News: 1973 March (Offsite-box 758, Folder 10)
    - Duplicates: Public Affairs: "New Perceptions" Conference: Bevedit: 1972 Sept. 29 - Oct. 30 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 11)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: News tour, 1975 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 12)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Reporter's committee on freedom of the press: 1973 March (Offsite-box 758, Folder 13)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Sutton's speech on reading and magazines: 1972 October 25 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 14)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Time covers of congressmen, 1964 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 15)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Time Inc. congressional dinners, memos to Hedley Donovan, etc.: 1972 September (Offsite-box 758, Folder 16)
    - Duplicates: Public affairs: Washington foreign policy seminar: 1974 November 11-12 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 17)
    - Duplicates: Publicity: Futures, 1974 (Offsite-box 758, Folder 18)